<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The French King's declaration of war against the Hollanders.</title>
            <title> English</title>
            <author>France. Sovereign (1643-1715 : Louis XIV)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B32769</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 807.g.5.[48]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232415</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99888873</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99888873</idno>
            <idno type="VID">196400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B32769)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 196400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; F2:3[45])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The French King's declaration of war against the Hollanders.</title>
                  <title> English</title>
                  <author>France. Sovereign (1643-1715 : Louis XIV)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Re-printed;,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: Given at Versailles, the 26th of November 1688.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History, Military --  1643-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:196400:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The <hi>French King's</hi> Declaration of War againſt the <hi>Hollanders.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AFter all that his Majeſty hath done to give Peace to <hi>Europe,</hi> the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant places he hath reſtored to attain to the Treaty concluded at <hi>Nimeguen</hi> in the year 1678, and the care he has ſince taken, not only for the Eſtabliſhment of the Truce, but alſo for the changing it into a perpetual Peace, his Majeſty had reaſon to hope, that the States-General of the United Provinces of the <hi>Low Countreys,</hi> who had ſhewn ſo much earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtneſs for the concluſion of that Truce, would have been no leſs zealous for the maintaining of it. In the mean time his Majeſty has had divers Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices for ſeveral months paſt, That the ſaid <hi>States</hi> ſuffering themſelves to be carried away by the deſires of thoſe who have no other intentions than to ſee a War begun again in <hi>Europe,</hi> were making extraordinary Levies and Preparations, and entring into Engagements with ſeveral Princes of the <hi>Empire,</hi> to hinder, by all manner of ways, the Eſtabliſhment of the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of <hi>Fuſtemberg</hi> in the Electorate of <hi>Cologne.</hi> And his Majeſty finding himſelf obliged to ſupport the Intereſts of the ſaid Cardinal, whoſe Election was poſitively declared to be oppoſed againſt all manner of Forms, only becauſe he was believed to be engaged in his Majeſties Intereſts; He exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſaid <hi>States-General,</hi> by his Ambaſſador the Count <hi>d'Avaux,</hi> not to employ the extraordinary Forces they were raiſing in any thing that might diſturb the Quiet of <hi>Europe;</hi> and cauſed it to be declared to them in expreſs terms, that he ſhould look upon what they attempted againſt the Cardinal of <hi>Fuſtemberg,</hi> as if it were againſt his own Dominions: His Majeſty has been ſince informed that they have not forborn to begin the execution of their projects; and that they have drawn together an Army under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Prince <hi>Waldeck,</hi> which is actually joyned with the Forces of the Princes that are leagued together againſt the Intereſt of the Cardinal of <hi>Furſtemberg;</hi> Which his Majeſty being no longer willing to diſſemble, has reſolved to declare War, as he doth by theſe Preſents, againſt the ſaid <hi>States-General</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> as well by Sea as by Land. His Majeſty for this effect commands and enjoyns all his Subjects; Vaſſals and Servants to fall upon the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> and has expreſly forbidden, and does forbid the having henceforward any Communication, Commerce or Intelligence with them upon pain of death. And to this end his Majeſty does revoke all Permiſſions, Paſsports, Safeguards, and Safe Conducts that may have been granted by himſelf, or his Lieutenant-Generals; and other his Officers contrary to theſe preſents; and has declared; and does declare them to be <hi>null;</hi> and of no <hi>effect</hi> and <hi>force;</hi> forbidding all perſons whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever to have any reſpect to them. His <hi>Majeſty</hi> orders and commands; that the Lord <hi>Admiral; Mareſchals</hi> of <hi>France; Governors</hi> and <hi>Lieutenant-Generals</hi> for his <hi>Majeſty</hi> in his <hi>Provinces</hi> and <hi>Armies; Mareſchals de Camp; Colonels; Captains; Commanders</hi> &amp; <hi>Conducters of his Forces</hi> as well <hi>Horſe as Foot; French</hi> &amp; <hi>Forreigners;</hi> and all other his <hi>Officers</hi> to whom it ſhall appertain; to cauſe the Contents of theſe Preſents to be put in execution; within the extent of their reſpective Powers and Juriſdictions; for ſuch is his Majeſties Pleaſure. He wills alſo and enjoyns; that theſe Preſents be publiſhed and affixed in all the Towns as well <hi>Maritime</hi> as others; and in all the <hi>Ports; Harbours;</hi> and all other places of his Kingdom; and the Territories under his obedience; where it ſhall be needful; to the end none may pretend cauſe of Ignorance. <hi>Given at</hi> Verſailles <hi>the</hi> 26th <hi>of</hi> November 1688. <hi>Sign'd</hi> Louis; <hi>and underneath</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN;</hi> Re-printed; 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
